Guide to the Kembra Pfahler Papers MSS.425
Fales Library and Special Collections
Kembra Pfahler Papers
1961-2015
1989-2002
Fales Library and Special Collections
Pfahler, Kembra
MSS.425
15.25 Linear Feet in 17 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 small flat box, 1 oversize flat box, 2 flat-file folders, 4 folders in a shared manuscript box, and 4 oversized folders in shared boxes.
The Kembra Pfahler Papers (1961-2015) documents the personal life and professional career of filmmaker, artist, musician, actress, and model Kembra Pfahler. This collection has significant documentation on her theatrical rock band, The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black (TVHKB), co-founded in 1988 with her first husband Samoa Moriki. The majority of the collection consists of photographs of the band on and off stage and publicity photo shoots, many taken by New York-based photographers. Band press clippings, handwritten lyrics, costume drawings, setlists, publicity material, and posters are also in this collection. Pfahler's performance art pieces and filmmaking with members of the Cinema of Transgression film group are documented through photographs, still footage, and promotional material. Photographs from her modeling career, fashion line, and art exhibitions are also in this collection. Materials from Pfahler's personal life include correspondence, press clippings, as well as a significant amount of photographs. Subjects of these materials include her family, first husband Samoa Moriki, partner Colin de Land, travel, and pets, as well as portraits of Pfahler from early childhood to adulthood.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Kembra Pfahler, 2015. The accession number associated with this purchase is 2015.425.
Appraisal
The following were removed from the collection: 2 optical discs (commercial and blank), material containing private health and financial information, and duplicates of print material and photographs.
Arrangement
Organized in two series:
Series I. The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black (Band)
Series II. Personal and Project Files
The files within each series are grouped by subject and arranged chronologically within.
Scope and Contents
The Kembra Pfahler Papers (dated 1961-2015) document Pfahler's work as a filmmaker, artist, actress, model, and rock musician. This collection contains a significant number of photographs chronicling the path of Pfahler and Samoa Moriki's New York City-based theatrical rock band The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black (TVHKB) both on and off the stage while they performed in New York City clubs including CBGB and the Marquee, and on tour throughout the United States during the late 1980s to the early 2000s. Many of the photographs were taken by New York-based photographers including Laure Leber, Katrina del Mar, Steve Glemboski, and Tina Paul. Pfahler's handwritten music lyrics, setlists, scrapbooks, costume sketches, press clippings, and promotional fliers and posters provide insight into a Lower East Side band that incorporated performance art and music into their stage shows. Images of their glam rock and dark humor performances in this collection include graphic nudity and simulated sexual acts. Their costuming typically included members with painted naked bodies, wigs, false rotted teeth, and handmade costumes and props created by Pfahler and other members.
Outside of the band, Pfahler pursued adjacent careers including her participation in the 1980s underground film movement Cinema of Transgression, which used shock value and black humor in film. This collection contains documentation of some of her films including photographs, film stills, promotional material, and a set of stills with New York artists and fellow Cinema of Transgression members Nick Zedd and Annie Sprinkle as actors. Her acting work is represented in this collection through video sleeve covers and promotional material from 1990s fetish films which include imagery of BDSM and other simulated sex acts. Pfahler's work as a print and runway model is depicted in both photographs and publications in this collection, including photographs taken by Rosalie Knox, Annie Sprinkle, Laure Leber, and Richard Kern, some of which include nudity and sexual situations. Her work as a performance and visual artist dates from the 1980s to 2010s and is represented in this collection through photograph documentation of performances, exhibition spaces, installations of her drawings and self-portraits, and notes, as well as promotional material for openings and events. These performances and artworks often depict Pfahler in her Karen Black character, with her naked body painted, wearing a black wig and false rotten teeth, and sometimes include other members from TVHKB. This collection also contains drawings, notes, press clippings, and runway show photographs related to Pfahler's clothing line from the early 2000s. Materials from Pfahler's personal life include correspondence, ephemera, and press clippings, as well as a significant amount of photographs of Pfahler's friends, family, travels, portraits of Pfahler, first husband Samoa Moriki, and partner Colin de Land.
Biographical Note
Kembra Pfahler (1961- ) is an American filmmaker, performance artist, musician, actress, and model based in New York City. After moving to New York in the early 1980s, she became involved in the underground film movement Cinema of Transgression. In 1988 she co-founded a band, The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black, with her first husband, Samoa Moriki. The group, which is still active as of 2024, is a theatrical rock band inspired by glam, punk, and shock rock. As a visual artist, Pfahler is known for her self-portraits and performance art pieces.
Related Materials
The Colin de Land collection (Identifier: AAA.delacoli) is at the Archives of American Art and contains photographs of Kembra Pfahler.
Performance art -- 20th century; Performance art -- 21st century.; Artists and community -- New York (N.Y); Performance art -- New York (N.Y); Lyric sheets.; Color photographs.; Posters.; Concerts.; Rock music.; Promotional materials; Musicians -- 20th century; Rock musicians.; Avant-garde (Music) -- New York (N.Y.) -- 20th century; Experimental theater -- 20th century; Glam rock music; Pfahler, Kembra; Moriki, Samoa; Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black (Musical group); Zedd, Nick; Sprinkle, Annie, 1954-; De Land, Colin, 1955-2003; Kern, Richard, 1954-; Halsband, Michael; Leber, Laure; Paul, Tina; Lacy, Mark Anthony; del Mar, Katrina; Glemboski, Steve
- Series I. The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black (Band), 1989-2008; 10 Linear Feet in 10 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 oversized flat box, 1 flat-file folder, and 3 folders in a shared oversized flat box.
  Scope and Contents
  This series primarily consists of photographs, as well as paper material related to Kembra Pfahler and Samoa Moriki's New York City-based glam rock band, The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black (TVHKB). This series contains material dating from the late 1980s to the 2000s when the band was most active and performing in New York City clubs including the Kitchen, Ritz, CBGB, Pyramid, Marquee, and Boy Bar, as well as summer tours in 1994 and 1995. The majority of this series chronicles their performances through photographs by multiple New York-based photographers including Laure Leber, Katrina del Mar, Steve Glemboski, and Tina Paul. These glam rock-style, darkly humorous performances often include large props, graphic nudity, and simulated sexual acts. Many performances included a segment where Pfahler, dressed as her Karen Black character, wearing a wig and false rotted teeth in full body paint performing a handstand while band members dressed as bunnies cracked eggs filled with coloring onto Pfahler's vaginal area. Photographs in this series also document the band's pre-show preparations including painting their naked bodies, attaching wigs and false teeth, and doning costumes, as well as post-show images of the band meeting fans, socializing with each other, and the removal of their body paint in small utility sinks and showers backstage during their tours. Images of photo shoot with the band were produced for use on posters, announcements, and album covers. Most of these photographs were taken by New York photographers including Richard Kern, Annie Sprinkle, Michael Halsband, and Michael Levine.
  A small collection of handwritten music lyrics, setlists, stage directions, tour scrapbooks, press clippings, and Pfahler's costume sketches are in this series, along with promotional material including show posters, telephone cards with the band image, and event annoucements. This series also includes graphics, mock-up boards, and release event posters for their albums include Neiborachie - The Guy Next Door and A National Health Care.
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related -- Live at the Kitchen, New York City, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related -- The Marquee, New York City, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, January 23, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs by Laure Leber -- Performances and Related, 1992, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs by Tina Paul -- Performances and Related, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs by Don Lewis -- Performances and Related, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related -- Summer Tour, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs by Mark Anthony Lacy -- Performances and Related, 1994-1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs by Katrina del Mar -- Performances and Related, 1994-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related -- Summer Tour, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Photographs by Justin Dupre -- Performances and Related, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs / View-Master Reel -- Performance at EJ's, October 30, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs by Glenn Dawney -- Performances and Related, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs by Howard Levenson -- Performances and Related, December 1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs by Iggy Segovia -- Performances and Related, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, 1998, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Photographs by Norman Blake -- Performances and Related, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs by Mary Ellenberger -- Performances and Related, circa 1989-2000s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs by Steve Glemboski -- Performances and Related, circa 1989-2000s (Box 3, Folder 6-8, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs by Rosalie Knox -- Performances and Related, circa 1989-2000s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs by Mark Anthony Lacy -- Performances and Related at the Limelight, New York City, circa 1989-2000s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs -- Album Party for The Anti-Naturalists, circa 1989-2010 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs -- Performance and Related -- Ritz, New York City, circa 1989-2000s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, circa 1989-2000s (Box 4, Folder 7-11, Box 5, Folder 1-8)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, circa 1989-2000s (Box 6, Folder 1-6, Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs -- Performances and Related, circa 1989-2000s (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Photographs by Richard Kern -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoots, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs by Kim Fielding -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoots, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs by Michael Halsband -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoots, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoots, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoots, circa 1989-2000s (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photographs -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoot in California Dry Lakebed, circa 1989-2000s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Photographs by Michael Levine -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoots, circa 1989-2000s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photographs -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoots, circa 1989-2000s (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs by Annie Sprinkle -- Publicity or Album Photo Shoot, circa 1989-2000s (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Press Clippings, 1989-1996, undated (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Lyrics, Setlists, Performance Notes, circa 1989-2000s (Box 8, Folder 5-8, Box 9, Folder 1-4, Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 2)
  - Lyrics and Setlists, circa 1989-2000s (Box 19, Folder 9, Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Lyrics, 1991-1992 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Pfahler's Drawings for Band Costumes and Logos, circa 1989-2000s (Box 9, Folder 5, Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 4)
  - Performance Advertisements and Promotional Mailers, circa 1989-2000s (Box 9, Folder 6, Box 20, Folder Unknown)
  - Band Graphics, Logos, Telephone Calling Cards with Band Images, circa 1989-2000s (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Notes, circa 1989-2000s (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Album -- Neiborachie - The Guy Next Door -- Phonographic Disc with Cover, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Album -- Mock-up Boards for A National Health Care, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Albums -- Graphics and Mockups for Various CD Covers for Band, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Posters -- Band Performances at CBGB, 1990, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Posters -- Band Performance / Premiere of Sewing Circle Film, 1992, undated (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
  - Posters -- Performance for Whitney Biennial, March 14, 2008 (Flat-file-folder 1)
  - Posters -- Band Performances, circa 1989-2000s (Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 1, Flat-file-folder 1)
  - Posters -- Album Releases and Concert Film Release, 1996, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Poster -- Album Release of The Anti-Naturalists, 1995 (Flat-file-folder 3)
  - Graphic and Order Form for Band T-Shirt Containing Image of Pfahler's Sewing Circle Performance, circa 1992-2000s (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Tour and Management Notebook, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Band Fashion Show "Anti-Naturalists" -- Photographs, Promotional Mailers, Notes, Poster, April 1, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 13, Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Promotional -- Ultra Mega 'Zine #5 Special Edition, Including Album Neiborachie - The Guy Next Door and Article About Touring with the Band, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Anti-Naturalists Summer Tour Scrapbook, Summer 1995 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Unholy Graphic Book Containing Band Imagery, and Colored Ink Drawing By Mike Diana, 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 3, Flat-file-folder 3)
- Series II. Personal and Project Files, 1961-2015; 8.25 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, 1 small flat box, 1 flat-file folder, 4 folders in a shared manuscript box, and 2 oversized folders in shared boxes
  This series contains material, a majority of which are photographs, related to projects Pfahler pursued outside of the band, as well as personal files and photographs. Pfahler's participation in the 1980s underground film movement Cinema of Transgression, is well documented in this series through handmade fliers, posters, correspondence, and photgraphic stills for Murder Mysteries, Historic Beauty Treatments, Cornella: The Story of a Burning Bush, and Mild Seven: The Cowboy Stories. Film stills for Trilogy of Teri include fellow-artists Nick Zedd and Annie Sprinkle as actors. The series also contains material documenting her film acting through video sleeve covers and promotional material for 1990s fetish films, which depict imagery of BDSM and other simulated sex acts. Film stills and on-set photographs for her acting jobs in Boys on the Side and Ferrum 5000 are also in this series.
  Her performance art career is well-represented in this series, including photographic documentation and promotional material dating from 1984 to 1987 for Pfahler's early performance art group, Oroboro, which often included her husband/fellow band member, Samoa. Later performance art pieces dating from the 1990s and 2000s include Pfahler as her Karen Black character, with her naked body painted, wearing a black wig and false rotting teeth. She is photographed in various locations, sometimes also with members of the Karen Black band in costume as well. Some performance art pieces were later produced as videos/films, including her 1996 Punk Ladies of Wrestling (PLOW) event and film. Material for PLOW includes photographs, a press release, and promotional material for the film.
  Pfahler's work as a visual artist shown through drawings and photographic self-portraits date from the early 2000s to 2010. Many of the works were exhibited at New York galleries. Her openings often included a performance art piece and/or band performances. Images of installations, opening parties, and performances are in this series, as well as exhibition artwork lists, notes, posters, and announcements. These performances and artworks often include Pfahler in her Karen Black character. Examples include the 2003 exhibition Kembra Pfahler: Availabism and Anti-Naturalism: A Feminine Experiment (which included a live performance of A Star is Born: The Horror Version), Womanizer in 2008, and Giverny with artist E.V. Day in 2012.
  Pfahler's work as a print and runway model is depicted in both photographs, publications, and press clippings in this series, including images depicting nudity, fetishism, BDSM, and other sexual situations. Modeling photographers include Rosalie Knox, Laure Leber, Rick Owens, and Richard Kern. This series also contains drawings, notes, press clippings, ephemera, and runway show photographs related to Pfahler's clothing line from the early 2000s. This series contains a small amount of personal correspondence and press clippings, as well as a significant amount of photographs of friends; family; first husband Samoa Morika; partner Colin de Land; childhood, teen, and adult portraits of Pfahler; and trips to Japan, Cape Cod, and Hawaii.
  - Early Ephemera -- Souvenir Hospital Certificate, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Photographs -- Pfahler Early Childhood, as Teen, and Family, circa 1962-1987 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Photographs -- Pfahler and Samoa Trip to Japan, circa 1986-1989 (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographs -- Disassembled Albums with Pfahler, Samoa, Some Performances, 1982-1986, 1990s (Box Shared Fales 108, Folder 3-6)
  - Photographs -- Pfahler, Samoa, Friends, Family, Pets, circa 1986-2000s (Box 10, Folder 9-10, Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Photographs -- "Souvenir of the Sprinkle Salon" Collage Featuring Pfahler and Samoa, October 1988 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Photographs -- Pfahler Casual Portraits, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Photograph -- Self-Portrait as Karen Black Character, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Photographs -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character, January 1998 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Photographs -- Pfahler, Colin de Land, Travel, Parties, 2001-2003 (Box 11, Folder 4-9, Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - Photographs -- Travel, Self-Portraits, 2002-2003 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Photographs -- Pfahler Holographic Image within a Cube, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Drawings -- Pfahler's Tattoo Ideas (1983), Figures, 1983, undated (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, 1983-2006, 2013 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Oroboro Ensemble Promotional Fliers and Project Booklet, 1984-1985, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Photographs, 1984-1986 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Poster "Live Acts" with Pfahler, Samoa, and Edgar Oliver at Pyramid, September 2, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character -- Photographs, 1996-2002 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character in Germany Locations -- Photographs, circa 2001-2003 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler and Women from the Band as Karen Black Characters -- Photographs, June 2001 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character -- Photographs by Bruce LaBruce, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character Doing a Polar Plunge -- Photographs, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler and Women from the Band as Karen Black Characters -- Photographs, June 2006 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler and Women from the Band as Karen Black Characters with Flag -- Photographs, 2008 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler and Women from the Band as Karen Black Characters Performing The Wall of Vagina -- Book Mock-up and Book Proof, circa 2009 (Box 13, Folder 6-8)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character in Los Angeles Locations -- Photographs, circa 1989-2000s (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character Nailing Down a Man's Tongue -- Photographs, circa 1989-2000s (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler and Women from the Band as Karen Black Characters -- Photographs, circa 1989-2000s (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler and Women from the Band as Karen Black Characters -- Photographs by Rosalie Knox, circa 1989-2000s (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Egg-Cracking Performance in Apartment, with Pfahler and Other Karen Black Character Performer -- Photographs, circa 1989-2000s (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Egg-Cracking Performance onto Unknown Man in the Liberace Museum Parking Lot -- Photographs, circa 1989-2000s (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- Pfahler as Karen Black Character -- Photographs, circa 1989-2000s (Box 14, Folder 2, Flat-file-folder 3)
  - Performance Art Documentation -- The Sewing Circle -- Photograph, circa 1990s (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Filmmaking -- Murder Mysteries and Historic Beauty Treatments -- Handmade Promotional Fliers and Posters, 1984, circa 1980s (Box 14, Folder 9, Box Shared Fales 110, Folder 3)
  - Filmmaking -- Mooziki la Moo-engo: Historical Consort from the Manual of Action -- Poster, January 20, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Filmmaking -- Cornella: The Story of a Burning Bush -- Photographic Stills, Rights Agreement, 1985, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 4, Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Filmmaking -- From the Manual of Action -- Poster for Film Premiere and Performance, October 31, 1986 (Flat-file-folder 1)
  - Filmmaking -- Mild Seven: The Cowboy Stories -- Photographic Stills, Handmade Event Fliers, Luzern Film Festival Letter, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Filmmaking -- Trilogy of Teri -- Still Images with Nick Zedd and Annie Sprinkle, circa 1987 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Filmmaking -- Unknown Project -- Still Images with Pfahler and Samoa, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Filmmaking -- Mock-up Brochure for Pfahler's Films Available for Purchase, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Filmmaking -- Still Images from Various Unknown Projects, circa 1980s (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Filmmaking -- Anima Sola -- Photographic Stills, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Filmmaking (as Actor) -- Boys on the Side -- On Set As Actor Photographs, circa 1994-1995 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Filmmaking (as Actor) -- Advertisements and VHS Tape Box Cover for Fetish Films, 1995, undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Filmmaking (as Actor) -- Ferrum 5000 -- Film Stills and On Set Photographs, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Filmmaking (as Actor) -- Unknown Film -- Posing with Other Actors On the Set, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Filmmaking -- The Girls of the Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black Movie -- Film Stills and VHS Tape Box Cover, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 15)